Rienow, Robert; Papers ua902.009
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
- Writings, 1937-1980; 3; 2.5 cubic ft.
  In this series are manuscripts and drafts of articles and book chapters written by Rienow, both alone and in cooperation with his wife. In many cases there are multiple drafts of the same article. Many of the drafts include handwritten corrections and annotations by Rienow. These files also include clippings and handwritten notes used in the creation of drafts and manuscripts, as well as occasional correspondence with publishers. Most of the writings relate to Rienow's political science or environmental interests. These include articles on the American standard of living and nuclear fallout, and contributions to the Book of Knowledge and the World Book Encyclopedia on United States government. A number of manuscripts, many of which were co-authored with Leona Train Rienow, are satirical looks at American and European society, including travel articles such as "What! No Lather?" Also found in this series are several drafts of Leona Train Rienow's 1970 novel The Year of the Last Eagle, to which Robert Rienow contributed, as well as a draft of her 1948 novel The Bewitched Caverns.
  - "Adirondacks Up for Grabs", Undated (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 1)
    Drafts and Notes.
  - "AEC: The Little Empire Within", Undated; manuscript and clippings (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 2)
  - The African Line of March, Drafts, Correspondence and Clippings, 1937 (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 3)
  - American Government in Today's World, Second Edition Promotional Poster, Undated (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 4)
  - American Problems Today, Outline and Correspondence, 1956-1958 (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 5)
  - "American Standard of Living-Not for Export", 1951-1958 (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 6)
    Draft, Notes and Clippings.
  - "Anarchy of the Commons", Draft, Undated (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 7)
  - "Are Our Rivers Getting Too Hot to Live With?", ca. 1959 (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 8)
    Draft and Clippings.
  - "The Assassination Belt", 1960 (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 9)
    Drafts and Clippings.
  - "Atomic Ignorance", 1958-1959 (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 10)
    Drafts, Correspondence, and Notes.
  - "The Battle for Children's Minds", Undated (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 11)
    Draft, Correspondence, and Notes.
  - "Beat the Atomic Age", 1957-1959 (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 12)
    Manuscripts, Notes, and Clippings.
  - The Bewitched Caverns, Leona Train Rienow, Manuscript, Undated (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 13)
  - "A Bit of a Go", Draft, Undated (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 14)
  - Book Drafts: Chapters 1-2 and 4, Undated (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 15)
  - Book Drafts: Chapter 5-International Bureaucracy, Chapter 8-Aristocracy of Conscience, Undated (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 16)
  - Book of Knowledge, "United States Congress", Undated (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 17)
  - Book of Knowledge, "United States Constitution", Undated (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 18)
  - Book of Knowledge, "United States Government", Undated (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 19)
  - Book Reviews, Miscellaneous, 1963-1972; Undated (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 20)
  - "Bursting With Pride", Manuscript, Undated (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 21)
  - "Can Our Rivers Be Saved?", 1960-1961 (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 22)
    Manuscript, Correspondence, and Clippings.
  - Compton's Articles, Drafts, and Correspondence, 1955-1958 (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 23)
  - Compton's Current, "U.S. Government", 1961-1963 (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 24)
  - Conklin, Roscoe, Untitled Article on, Drafts and Notes, Undated (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 25)
  - "Constitutional Amendments-Off Limits for the Governor?", 1959 (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 26)
    Draft, Correspondence, and Clippings.
  - "Consumer Cooperatives" (Chapter XXI), Undated (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 27)
    Manuscript and Notes.
  - Contemporary International Politics, Notes and Clippings, 1961 (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 28)
  - "The Darkening Veil", Manuscript, Drafts, and Correspondence, 1957 (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 29)
  - "Darker Side of Science/Dozen Ways to Beat the Atomic Age", Outline and Drafts, Undated (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 30)
  - Design of Dictatorship, Manuscript, 1938 (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 31)
  - Design of Dictatorship, Manuscript and Clipping, 1938 (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 32)
  - The Disposal of Waste Oil in Albany County, Report, 1974 (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 33)
  - "Does the World Need a New Lincoln?", 1962 (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 34)
  - "Earth's Torment: The Sovereign State", Draft, Undated (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 35)
  - Elite-the Dilemma of the Make-Believe Democracies, Drafts and Clippings, Undated (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 36)
  - "Emerging Africa", ca. 1966 (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 37)
  - Encyclopedia Article Sources, Notes and Comments, 1961-1963 (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 38)
  - "Fighting for Peer Life", Draft, Undated (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 39)
  - "Fined: Fifty Billion Dollars!", ca. 1940-1941 (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 40)
  - "Forests and Skyscrapers", Manuscript, Undated (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 41)
  - "Going Places", Draft, Undated (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 42)
  - "How to Tell a Big Shot", ca. 1964 (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 43)
  - "How We Pay for Our Jury Dodging/Does the World Need a New Lincoln?", 1961 (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 44)
    Outline, Notes, and Correspondence.
  - "Illusions of Internationalism", Drafts, ca. 1974 (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 45)
    [Contains copy of The Nation].
  - Income Tax, Notes, Undated (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 46)
  - "La France Dit 'Non'", Undated (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 47)
  - "The Last Boss Sits Tight", 1961-1962 (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 48)
    Drafts, Notes and Clippings.
  - "Lawmaking for the Commons", Draft, Undated (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 49)
  - The Lonely Quest, Presidential Speech/Follow-up, Drafts, Clippings, and Notes, 1963-1967 (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 50)
  - "Manifesto for the Sea", Manuscript and Drafts, Undated (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 51)
  - "Manifesto from Halfway Up the Wall", Correspondence, Manuscripts, and Drafts, 1974 (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 52)
  - "Marx Was an Alien", Draft, Undated (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 53)
  - Metropolitan Maze, Notes, Undated (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 54)
  - Miscellaneous Manuscripts, Undated (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 55)
  - Moment in the Sun, Draft, Undated (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 56)
  - Moment in the Sun, Miscellaneous, 1967-1973 (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 57)
  - "Mutiny After the Bounty", 1939 (Box 1 (3-Writings), Folder 58)
  - Natural Resources, Miscellaneous Articles, Undated (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 1)
  - "A New Look at Taxes", Manuscript, Outline, and Background Materials, 1963 (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 2)
  - "New Poisons in Our Streams", Draft, Undated (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 3)
  - "The New Presidency and the Cities", 1963 (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 4)
    Research Proposal and Clippings.
  - "Newspaper Know-How", Undated (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 5)
    Draft and Notes.
  - Of Snuff, Sin, and the Senate, "The Deep Pocket in the Black Frock Coat", Undated (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 6)
  - Of Snuff, Sin, and the Senate, "The Lusty Buccaneers", Undated (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 7)
  - Of Snuff, Sin and the Senate, Drafts, Notes, and Clippings, Undated (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 8)
  - Of Snuff, Sin and the Senate, Manuscript, Notes, and Clippings, Undated (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 9)
  - Of Snuff, Sin and the Senate, "Prophecy of Doom", Undated (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 10)
  - Of Snuff, Sin and the Senate, "Togas for Sale", Undated (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 11)
  - "One Man, One Vote", 1960-1963 (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 12)
    Drafts, Notes, and Clippings.
  - "The Opening Door to Teaching", Manuscript, Undated (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 13)
  - "Ordeal by Oil", Draft and Correspondence, 1961 (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 14)
  - "Our Colonial Guilt Complex-Let's Shove It!" Outline and Drafts, Undated (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 15)
  - Our New Life with the Atom, Correspondence and Clippings, 1958-1960 (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 16)
  - Our New Life with the Atom, Partial Draft, Notes and Clippings, Undated (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 17)
  - "Our Stake in Wilderness", Undated (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 18)
  - "A Parable in Power", Undated (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 19)
  - Paradise for Cats/Puss's Paradise, Drafts, Undated (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 20)
  - "People People Everywhere", Draft and Outline, Undated (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 21)
  - Perfidy at the Polls, Notes, Undated (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 22)
  - "Poison in the Rain", Manuscript, Drafts, and Correspondence, 1961 (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 23)
  - "Politics of Destruction/You'll Feel It in Your Bones", Drafts and Correspondence, 1957 (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 24)
  - "The Propaganda Weapon on the World Scene", Manuscript and Correspondence, 1959-1960 (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 25)
  - Publications, Reviews and Promotion, 1955-1956 (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 26)
  - "Red Tape Makes Me Blush", Draft, Undated (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 27)
  - Research Notes, Undated (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 28)
  - "The Rest Room Circuit", Drafts and Correspondence, 1964 (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 29)
  - "The 'Rue-It Yourself' Era", 1959 (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 30)
    Proposal, Correspondence, and Notes.
  - Sewers and Cesspools, Untitled Article, Drafts, Undated (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 31)
  - "The Sicker Sex", Manuscript and Correspondence, 1952 (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 32)
  - "Silence in the Galleries", Draft, Undated (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 33)
  - "Some Forgotten Slants on Selective Service", Drafts and Manuscript, Undated (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 34)
  - Swamps and Marches, Two Articles, ca. 1959 (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 35)
  - "The Surrender to Cynicism", Manuscript and Correspondence, 1939 (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 36)
  - The Test of the Nationality of a Merchant Vessel, Outline and First Chapter, 1937 (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 37)
  - Texts Are Tools, Drafts, Correspondence and Notes, 1952-1958 (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 38)
  - "Those Peregrinating Plants", Drafts, Manuscript, and Correspondence, 1957 (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 39)
  - "Trifle with Cream", Draft, Undated (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 40)
  - "Urbiculture", ca. 1960 (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 41)
  - "Water Famine-How Far Ahead?", 1958-1961 (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 42)
  - "West Point, Farewell", Manuscripts, Drafts, and Correspondence, 1931 (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 43)
  - "What! No Lather?" Draft, Undated (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 44)
  - "What? No Soap?", Undated (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 45)
    Draft and Clipping.
  - "What We Don't Know About Our Political Parties", Drafts, 1960s (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 46)
  - "What We Don't Know About the Atom"/"We Want the Truth About the Atom", Drafts, 1958 (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 47)
  - "When a Writer Takes to the Road", Manuscript and Correspondence, 1967 (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 48)
  - "Why Isn't Puerto Rico in the UN?", 1961-1962 (Box 2 (3-Writings), Folder 49)
  - "Will Your Home Burn for Lack of Water?" Drafts, Manuscripts, and Correspondence, 1961 (Box 3 (3-Writings), Folder 1)
  - The World Book Encyclopedia, "Citizenship" and "Naturalization", 1956-1958 (Box 3 (3-Writings), Folder 2)
  - The World Book Encyclopedia, Notes, 1964 (Box 3 (3-Writings), Folder 3)
  - The Year of the Last Eagle, Draft, ca. 1968? (Box 3 (3-Writings), Folder 4)
  - The Year of the Last Eagle, Draft, ca. 1970 (Box 3 (3-Writings), Folder 5)
  - The Year of the Last Eagle, Draft, ca. 1970 (Box 3 (3-Writings), Folder 6)
  - The Year of the Last Eagle, Draft, ca. 1970 (Box 3 (3-Writings), Folder 7)
  - The Year of the Last Eagle, Draft, ca. 1970 (Box 3 (3-Writings), Folder 8)
  - The Year of the Last Eagle, Draft, ca. 1970 (Box 4 (3-Writings), Folder 1)
  - The Year of the Last Eagle, Draft, ca. 1970 (Box 4 (3-Writings), Folder 2)
  - The Year of the Last Eagle, Draft, ca. 1970 (Box 4 (3-Writings), Folder 3)
- Broadcasts, 1958-1969; 4; 1.8 cubic ft.
  This series contains scripts and supporting materials for broadcasts conducted by Rienow. Two lecture series predominate. The first, Living Patterns of Government, was a televised political science course broadcast in early 1958. The second, Man Against His Environment, was a 28 part radio lecture series which addressed a variety of environmental concerns. Topics include air and water pollution, overpopulation, deforestation of the wilderness, and overcrowding in cities. There are also files on other broadcasts by Rienow, such as "The Politics of Survival: The Image of the President.".
  Arranged alphabetically by title, then by lecture number and chronologically.
  - "The Energy Crisis", Undated (Box 1 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 1)
  - Fear of Citizens Today-Mass [democracy], Undated (Box 1 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 2)
  - Living Patterns of Government, Fan Mail, Enclosures, 1958 (Box 1 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 3)
  - Living Patterns of Government, Miscellaneous, 1958 (Box 1 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 4)
  - Living Patterns of Government, TV Scripts, 1958 (Box 1 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 5)
  - Living Patterns of Government, TV Scripts and Lecture, 1958 (Box 1 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 6)
  - Living Patterns of Government, TV Scripts, Notes, and Clippings, 1958 February (Box 1 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 7)
  - Living Patterns of Government, TV Scripts, Notes, and Clippings, 1958 March (Box 1 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 8)
  - Living Patterns of Government, TV Scripts, Notes, and Clippings, 1958 March (Box 1 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 9)
  - Living Patterns of Government, TV Scripts, Notes, and Clippings, 1958 March (Box 1 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 10)
  - Living Patterns of Government, TV Scripts, Notes, and Clippings, 1958 April (Box 1 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 11)
  - Living Patterns of Government, TV Scripts, Notes, and Clippings, 1958 April (Box 1 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 12)
  - Living Patterns of Government, TV Scripts, Notes, and Clippings, 1958 April (Box 1 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 13)
  - Living Patterns of Government, TV Scripts, Notes, and Clippings, 1958 May (Box 1 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 14)
  - Living Patterns of Government, TV Scripts, Outlines, and Notes, 1958 May (Box 1 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 15)
  - Living Patterns of Government, TV Scripts, Notes, and Clippings, 1958 May (Box 1 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 16)
  - Living Patterns of Government, TV Scripts, Clippings, and Notes, 1958 May (Box 1 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 17)
  - Man Against His Environment, Lecture 1, 1968-1969 (Box 1 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 18)
  - Man Against His Environment, Lecture 2, "Too Many People", 1968-1969 (Box 1 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 19)
  - Man Against His Environment, Lecture 3, "The Growth Panic", 1968-1969 (Box 1 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 20)
  - Man Against His Environment, Lecture 4, "Ever the Greatest Lean", 1968-1969 (Box 1 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 21)
  - Man Against His Environment, Lecture 6, "The Great American Thirst", 1968-1969 (Box 1 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 22)
  - Man Against His Environment, Lecture 5, 1968-1969 (Box 1 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 23)
  - Man Against His Environment, Lecture 7, "Water Witches of the Future", 1968-1969 (Box 1 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 24)
  - Man Against His Environment, Lecture 8, "Wilderness Our Wolf Mother", 1968-1969 (Box 1 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 25)
  - Man Against His Environment, Lecture 9, "Wilderness and the Civilized Animal", 1968-1969 (Box 1 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 26)
  - Man Against His Environment, Lecture 10, "When Man Plays God", 1968-1969 (Box 1 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 27)
  - Man Against His Environment, Lecture 11, "Parade of the Doomed", 1968-1969 (Box 2 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 1)
  - Man Against His Environment, Lecture 12, "The Agony of the Cities", 1968-1969 (Box 2 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 2)
  - Man Against His Environment, Lecture 13, "Strangulation By Freeway", 1968-1969 (Box 2 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 3)
  - Man Against His Environment, Lecture 14, "The Outfalls May Be Our Downfall", 1968-1969 (Box 2 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 4)
  - Man Against His Environment, Lecture 15, "Cold Statistics and Hot Pollution", 1968-1969 (Box 2 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 5)
  - Man Against His Environment, Lecture 16, "The Darkening Veil", 1968-1969 (Box 2 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 6)
  - Man Against His Environment, Lecture 17, "Air Rationing: The New Age", 1968-1969 (Box 2 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 7)
  - Man Against His Environment, Lecture 18, "Color Me Green", 1968-1969 (Box 2 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 8)
  - Man Against His Environment, Lecture 19, "A Dirty Four Letter Word", 1968-1969 (Box 2 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 9)
  - Man Against His Environment, Lecture 20, "To Hear or Not to Hear", 1968-1969 (Box 2 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 10)
  - Man Against His Environment, Lecture 21, "The Slow Kill", 1968-1969 (Box 2 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 11)
  - Man Against His Environment, Lecture 22, "No Place to Flee To", 1968-1969 (Box 2 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 12)
  - Man Against His Environment, Lecture 23, "What's Left in Davey Jones' Locker?", 1968-1969 (Box 2 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 13)
  - Man Against His Environment, Lecture 24, "The Salt in Our Blood", 1968-1969 (Box 2 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 14)
  - Man Against His Environment, Lecture 25, "The Escape Hatch", 1968-1969 (Box 2 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 15)
  - Man Against His Environment, Lecture 26, "The Big Snow Job", 1968-1969 (Box 2 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 16)
  - Man Against His Environment, Lecture 27, "Politics: Where the Big Show Down Is", 1968-1969 (Box 2 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 17)
  - Man Against His Environment, Lecture 28, "Earthmanship", 1968-1969 (Box 2 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 18)
  - Man Against His Environment, Miscellaneous, 1968-1969 (Box 2 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 19)
  - Man Against His Environment, Student Guide, 1969 (Box 2 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 20)
  - Overpopulation, Rough Drafts of Broadcasts, Notes, and Clippings, 1968-1971 (Box 2 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 21)
  - Overpopulation, Rough Drafts of Broadcasts, Notes, and Clippings, 1968-1971 (Box 2 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 22)
  - The Politics of Survival: Corruption at the Polls, Undated (Box 2 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 23)
  - The Politics of Survival: President's Image, 1961 (Box 2 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 24)
  - Radio Spots, 1971 (Box 2 (4-Broadcasts), Folder 25)
    [also includes clippings].
- Speeches and Lectures, 1938-1976; 5; 0.33 cubic ft.
  This series contains drafts of speeches and lectures presented by Rienow at various public functions as well as notes taken on the topic of the speech and occasionally clippings regarding the speech. There is also occasional correspondence between Rienow and the person or group for whom he is presenting. The majority of these speeches relate to Rienow's environmental interests. Topics include pollution, land use and nuclear fallout. A few speeches are on topics in political science and teaching, such as those presented to the Symposium on Citizenship Education.
  - "Alternatives to Burning", Undated (Box 1 (5-Speeches and Lectures), Folder 1)
  - BSCS/CONPASS Meeting, Presentation, 1970 (Box 1 (5-Speeches and Lectures), Folder 2)
  - Capital Area School Boards Institute, 1964 (Box 1 (5-Speeches and Lectures), Folder 3)
  - Clippings and Anecdotes for Speeches, 1965 (Box 1 (5-Speeches and Lectures), Folder 4)
  - Conservation Speeches, 1954-1957; Undated (Box 1 (5-Speeches and Lectures), Folder 5)
  - Hands Across the Gap, 1972 (Box 1 (5-Speeches and Lectures), Folder 6)
  - Loose Notes, Undated (Box 1 (5-Speeches and Lectures), Folder 7)
  - New York State Council for the Social Studies, Speech, 1966 February 10-1966 February 12 (Box 1 (5-Speeches and Lectures), Folder 8)
  - "The Park Program: It's Bigger Than You Think", Undated (Box 1 (5-Speeches and Lectures), Folder 9)
  - Politics of the Environment, Speeches, Undated (Box 1 (5-Speeches and Lectures), Folder 10)
  - "Politics of the Environment Backlash", Undated (Box 1 (5-Speeches and Lectures), Folder 11)
  - "Preying on the Preserve", 1956 (Box 1 (5-Speeches and Lectures), Folder 12)
  - Speeches, Miscellaneous, 1938-1960 (Box 1 (5-Speeches and Lectures), Folder 13)
  - Speeches, Miscellaneous, 1938-1960 (Box 1 (5-Speeches and Lectures), Folder 14)
  - Speeches, Miscellaneous, 1970; 1974; 1976; Undated (Box 1 (5-Speeches and Lectures), Folder 15)
  - Symposium on Citizenship Education, 1956 May 6-1956 May 7 (Box 1 (5-Speeches and Lectures), Folder 16)
  - "Tinkering With Education Is Not Enough", Colloquium on Environmental Education, 1970 (Box 1 (5-Speeches and Lectures), Folder 17)
  - "Wildlife in Peril: Mammals of the Land", Undated (Box 1 (5-Speeches and Lectures), Folder 18)
- Correspondence, 1939-1984; 6; 1.75 cubic ft.
  The majority of the correspondence in this series relates to Rienow's environmental activism. Included is correspondence with members of various environmental organizations, such as the Defenders of Wildlife and the Nature Conservancy, as well as letters written to policy makers such as New York State and United States Senators. Additional correspondence relates to Rienow's writing career, including correspondence with publishers, fan mail, and letters to Rienow asking him to speak at a variety of engagements. The series also contains personal correspondence between Rienow and family members as well as other friends or acquaintances such as Erastus Corning II, Mayor of the City of Albany, and Lady Bird Johnson.
  Arranged alphabetically and chronologically.
  - Book and Magazine Publishers, 1954-May 1959 (Box 1 (6-Correspondence), Folder 1)
  - Book and Magazine Publishers, 1959 June-1974 (Box 1 (6-Correspondence), Folder 2)
  - Book and Magazine Publishers, 1960-1968 (Box 1 (6-Correspondence), Folder 3)
  - Book and Magazine Publishers, 1961-1967 (Box 1 (6-Correspondence), Folder 4)
  - Book and Magazine Publishers, 1968-1980 (Box 1 (6-Correspondence), Folder 5)
  - Book of Knowledge, 1964-1966 (Box 1 (6-Correspondence), Folder 6)
  - Construction Companies, 1965 (Box 1 (6-Correspondence), Folder 7)
  - Corning, Erastus, 1967-1971 (Box 1 (6-Correspondence), Folder 8)
  - The Creaking Gate, 1973-1974 (Box 1 (6-Correspondence), Folder 9)
  - County Legislature Environmental, 1973; 1981 (Box 1 (6-Correspondence), Folder 10)
  - Defenders of Wildlife, 1971 (Box 1 (6-Correspondence), Folder 11)
  - Environmental, 1964-1973 (Box 1 (6-Correspondence), Folder 12)
  - Goldstein, Jerome, 1969 (Box 1 (6-Correspondence), Folder 13)
  - Goodfrey, Arthur, 1968-1981 (Box 1 (6-Correspondence), Folder 14)
  - Grafton, Wisconsin, 1975 (Box 1 (6-Correspondence), Folder 15)
  - Harry Walter Inc., Lectures, 1970-1972 (Box 1 (6-Correspondence), Folder 16)
  - Important Letters, 1965-1983 (Box 1 (6-Correspondence), Folder 17)
  - The Institute on Man and Science, 1967-1970 (Box 1 (6-Correspondence), Folder 18)
  - Literary Agents, 1972 (Box 1 (6-Correspondence), Folder 19)
  - The Lonely Quest, 1971 (Box 1 (6-Correspondence), Folder 20)
  - Man Against His Environment, 1969-1971 (Box 1 (6-Correspondence), Folder 21)
  - McGregor, Harvey, 1963-1965 (Box 1 (6-Correspondence), Folder 22)
  - Miscellaneous, 1939-1985 (Box 1 (6-Correspondence), Folder 23)
  - Miscellaneous, 1944-1966 (Box 1 (6-Correspondence), Folder 24)
  - Miscellaneous, 1948-1969 (Box 1 (6-Correspondence), Folder 25)
  - Miscellaneous, 1953-1968 (Box 1 (6-Correspondence), Folder 26)
  - Miscellaneous, 1953-1980 (Box 2 (6-Correspondence), Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1954-1972 (Box 2 (6-Correspondence), Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 1963-1980 (Box 2 (6-Correspondence), Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous, B, 1963-1981 (Box 2 (6-Correspondence), Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous, H, 1963-1981 (Box 2 (6-Correspondence), Folder 5)